John L. Cable Papers
John L. Cable Papers
1912-1964
Cable, John L. (John Levi), 1884-1971.
3 linear ft.
United States attorney and congressman from Ohio, particularly interested in questions of citizenship. Collection includes correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, photographs, published material, speeches and memorabilia.
3169512
Biographical History
John L. Cable (1884-1971) was an American attorney and a United States Congressman from Ohio. He graduated from Kenyon College (1906) and from George Washington University law school (1909). He served four terms as a United States Representative from Ohio (1921-1925 and 1929-1933), and was assistant to the Ohio Attorney General (1933-1937). Cable was also the author of several works on law and citizenship. The Cable Act of 1922, which revised citizenship laws relating to American women who married foreign nationals, was largely his work.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John L. Cable Papers consist of correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, photographs, published material, speeches and memorabilia.
Apart from two items (letters to Eisenhower and to George Romney), Correspondence is entirely incoming. Correspondents of interest include Admiraly Byrd, the American Lafayette Society, George Romney and J. Edgar Hoover.
Subject files include material on the Cable Act of 1922, articles about Cable, various certificates of membership and achievement, an official electoral college ballot from the presidential election of 1932, and miscellaneous items such as invitations, clippings, a congressional pass book, and others.
Manuscripts contains manuscripts authored by Cable on women's citizenship and notable citizenship court cases. The latter, a typescript in a large three-ring binder, may be an early draft of Cable's book Decisive Decisions of United States Citizenship.
Photographs consists of two items, one of Cable and one of a relative, Mary Hernley Cable.
Published material contains copies of books, pamphlets and articles by Cable and others. Included here are copies of three of Cable's books, as well as a memorial volume published on the death of his father, Davis J. Cable.
Speeches contains one given by Cable on the citizenship of George Washington and a bound collection of the text of speeches given by Cable before Congress.
Memorabilia consists of seven scrapbooks spanning some thirty years, One includes photostats of documents dated much earlier, perhaps accumulated as research notes for Cable's work on citizenship. There is also a George Washington Bicentennial commemorative pin.
Arrangement of the Collection
As above.
Separated Material
A copy of Cable's "American citizenship rights of women. Hearing before a subcommittee of the Committee on immigration, United States Senate, Seventy-second Congress, second session, on S. 992..." has been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics, government and public administration; Cable, John L. (John Levi), 1884-1971.; Cable, John L. (John Levi), 1884-1971. -- Loss of citizenship, denaturalization, the alien in wartime.; Cable, John L. (John Levi), 1884-1971. -- Rights and responsibilities at railway grade crossings; Hazard, Henry B. -- Administrative naturalization abroad of members of the armed forces of the United States; Holliday, W.T. -- World Law or World Anarchy: The Case for a World Federal Government; United States. -- Congress. -- Senate. -- Committee on Immigration.; Citizenship -- United States.; Legislators -- Ohio.; Married women -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States -- History.; Married women -- Nationality.; Naturalization -- United States.; Books.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches (documents); Lawyers.; Legislators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John L. Cable, 1965, 1967, 1973.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Adams, Sherman, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - American Friends of Lafayette, State Department, 1919; 1944-1962 (Box 1)
  - Byrd, R. E., 1930 (Box 1)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1954; undated; printed card, signed (Box 1)
  - Hatfield, Mark O., 1964 (Box 1)
  - Hoover, J. Edgar, 1958 (Box 1)
  - McCulloch, William M., 1953; 1955,; 1961 (Box 1)
  - Romney, George, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Wiley, Anna K., 1930 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Acts of Congress by John L. Cable (Box 1)
  - Articles about Cable (Box 1)
  - Cable Act, 1929-1931; on citizenship for women (Box 1)
  - Campaign material, 1924; undated (Box 1)
  - Certificates
    - Allen County Bar, membership, 1913 (Box 1)
    - General Accounting Office, 1925 (Box 1)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission, 1933 (Box 1)
    - Ohio State Bar, membership, 1908 (Box 1)
    - Ohio State Bar, 50 years, circa 1960 (Box 1)
    - Selective Service Board, Appeals Agent appointment, 1948; undated; 2 items (Box 1)
    - Selective Service Board, 10 years, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Selective Service Board, 15 years, 1963 (Box 1)
    - United States Supreme Court, "attorney and counselor of the Supreme Court", 1931 (Oversize 1)
  - Congressional Record, clipping (Box 1)
  - Electoral College, 1933; official final ballot (Box 1)
  - Official invitations (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, clippings, pass book, Congressional parking pass, more (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - "Famous Citizenship Cases by John L. Cable", 1963; typescript, in three-ring binder (Box 3)
  - "When is a woman an American?" (Box 1)
  - "Women's battle for citizenship" (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Of Cable, 1 item (Box 1)
  - Of others, circa 1885; Mary Hernley Cable (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Cable, John L. and others / Davis J. Cable 1859-1924, Cable's father; consists of tributes to him and a short biography by John Cable (Box 1)
  - Cable, John L. / Decisive Decisions of United States Citizenship and Loss of Citizenship — Denaturalization — The Alien in Wartime, 1943; 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - Cable, John L. / Rights and Responsibilities at Railway Grade Crossings, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Hazard, Henry B. / Administrative Naturalization Abroad of Members of the Armed Forces of the United States, 1952; reprint from The American Journal of International Law, vol. 46 no. 2 (Box 1)
  - Holliday, W.T. / World Law or World Anarchy: The Case for a World Federal Government, Aug 1949; article, American Bar Association Journal, vol. 35 (Box 1)
  - U.S. Department of Labor / Historical Sketch of Naturalization in the United States, 1927 (Box 1)
- Speeches
  - "The citizenship of George Washington", 1931 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous speeches before Congress, 1921-1924; 1 bound volume (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - George Washington Bicentennial medal, 1932; on pin/ribbon, with Cable's name engraved (Box 3)
  - Scrapbooks
    - untitled, long narrow volume, circa 1915-1921; clippings relating to campaign, citizenship, various legal cases of interest (Box 2)
    - "Scrap Book" on front in ornate white letters, photograph glued to front, 1921-1922; clippings (Box 2)
    - "SCRAP BOOK NUMBER THREE", 1922-1923; clippings; inside back cover is full page campaign ad for Cable (Box 2)
    - untitled, 1923-1924; clippings (Box 3)
    - "The Ideal Scrapbook" printed on front, large brown volume, 1928-1933; clippings relating to campaign, a few letters from constituents; much material detached from pages or never affixed (Oversize 1)
    - "SCRAP BOOK" on front, large green volume, 1930-1931; 1912,; 1947; clippings, telegrams, letters, includes photograph of daughter Mary from Washington DC Sunday Star (Oversize 1)
    - untitled, picture of three-masted schooner printed on front, negative photostats of statutes and other material relating to citizenship, originals are dated as early as 1770s (Oversize 1)